<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://daveflynn.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://daveflynn.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-13T15:37:13+08:00</updated><id>https://daveflynn.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">PipeRider</title><subtitle>Data Reliability Automated</subtitle><author><name>PipeRider</name></author><entry><title type="html">Ultimate Guide to automate data monitoring</title><link href="https://daveflynn.github.io/2022/09/13/data-monitoring-ultimate-guide.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ultimate Guide to automate data monitoring" /><published>2022-09-13T09:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-09-13T09:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://daveflynn.github.io/2022/09/13/data-monitoring-ultimate-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://daveflynn.github.io/2022/09/13/data-monitoring-ultimate-guide.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-is-data-monitoring">What is data monitoring?</h2>

<p>Data monitoring is the process of proactively reviewing and evaluating important business data to ensure quality and ascertain adherence to established standards and protocols. While this can be done manually, most contact centers use specialized software that provide all the data needed in the form of dashboards, alerts, and reports.</p>

<h2 id="benefits-of-data-monitoring">Benefits of data monitoring</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Maintain data accuracy: Automatically assess the quality of more than 200 metadata attributes within your data files.
    <ol>
      <li>Verify data fields for completeness, uniqueness, statistical anomalies, and more</li>
      <li>Receive automated alerts when data quality falls below a specified threshold</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Visualize quality changes: Show fluctuations in data quality levels over time with visual dashboards.
    <ol>
      <li>Validate the impacts of business rule changes on overall data quality</li>
      <li>Demonstrate program success to business leadership with helpful reports</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Empower business users: Provide permission-based access to business users to generate reports or transform data.
    <ol>
      <li>Create business-specific rules to monitor the data that is important to you</li>
      <li>Increase overall transparency into your organization’s data management practices</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Dave Flynn</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What is data monitoring?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ultimate Guide to automate data reliability</title><link href="https://daveflynn.github.io/2022/09/13/data-reliability-ultimate-guide.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ultimate Guide to automate data reliability" /><published>2022-09-13T09:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-09-13T09:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://daveflynn.github.io/2022/09/13/data-reliability-ultimate-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://daveflynn.github.io/2022/09/13/data-reliability-ultimate-guide.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="quick-takeaways">Quick Takeaways</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Reliable data is the key for organizations to make accurate and informed decisions</li>
  <li>To improve data reliability, start by assessing your current situation and then build a robust data infrastructure</li>
  <li>You need to clean existing data and then analyze and optimize new data creation and collection</li>
  <li>Data reliability improves when you break down data silos, integrate apps, organize your data, and employ robust reporting and dashboards</li>
</ul>

<p>Unreliable data can cost a business in many ways. Experts estimate that between 60% to 85% of all business initiatives fail because of poor quality data. There’s a real cost to unreliable data; Gartner reports that poor data quality costs the average organization between $9.7 million and $14.2 million each year.</p>

<p>Reliable data helps decision-makers take the guesswork out of the day-to-day and strategic decisions they have to make to keep their businesses running. Without reliable data, those same decisions become more tenuous and less accurate, ultimately affecting the success of the business.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-data-reliability">What is data reliability?</h2>

<p>Data reliability means that data is complete and accurate, and it is a crucial foundation for building data trust across the organization. Ensuring data reliability is one of the main objectives of data integrity initiatives, which are also used to maintain data security, data quality, and regulatory compliance.</p>]]></content><author><name>InfuseAI</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Quick Takeaways]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ultimate Guide to Data Observability</title><link href="https://daveflynn.github.io/2022/09/12/data-observability-ultimate-guide.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ultimate Guide to Data Observability" /><published>2022-09-12T15:25:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-09-12T15:25:00+08:00</updated><id>https://daveflynn.github.io/2022/09/12/data-observability-ultimate-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://daveflynn.github.io/2022/09/12/data-observability-ultimate-guide.html"><![CDATA[<p>Modern businesses obtain data across numerous tools and programs, but few have the visibility to see how these programs interact. Businesses may better comprehend, manage, and track their data across the entire tech stack with the aid of data observability.</p>

<p>We will explain what data observability is, how it differs from monitoring and data quality, and what kinds of information you can track using it. You’ll learn how to put data observability into practice and locate the best data observability solutions for your company at the end of this article.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-data-observability">What is Data Observability?</h2>

<p>Data observability is the capability to comprehend, assess, and control the state of the data across a variety of IT technologies during the course of the data lifecycle. Using telemetry data like logs, metrics, and traces, a data observability platform assists companies in identifying, prioritizing, and resolving real-time data issues.</p>

<p>Observability enables businesses to enhance security by tracking data transfer between various servers, applications, and tools. Businesses can maintain the internal health of their IT systems and streamline corporate data monitoring using data observability by examining outputs.</p>]]></content><author><name>Dave Flynn</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Modern businesses obtain data across numerous tools and programs, but few have the visibility to see how these programs interact. Businesses may better comprehend, manage, and track their data across the entire tech stack with the aid of data observability.]]></summary></entry></feed>