<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-10-03T09:50:33+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">PipeRider</title><subtitle>Data Reliability Automated</subtitle><author><name>PipeRider</name></author><entry><title type="html">Guide to Data Reliability</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/guide-to-data-reliability.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Guide to Data Reliability" /><published>2022-09-27T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-09-27T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/guide-to-data-reliability</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/guide-to-data-reliability.html"><![CDATA[<p>Modern organizations have gained unprecedented access to quantitative and qualitative data. With all this information available, it’s become best practice for every team to make data-driven decisions. But there’s a problem.</p>

<p>You may be collecting a large amount of information within your data stack, but are you certain that these data sets are complete, accurate, and up-to-date? If not, these data sets might cost you a lot.</p>

<p>IBM estimated that the yearly cost of poor quality data, in the US alone, in 2016, is a whopping $3.1 trillion. In 2021, Gartner reported that every year, unreliable data costs organizations an average of $12.9 million. And it’s safe to say that the number has very likely increased as data-driven decision-making is adopted by every business imaginable.</p>

<p>That’s why ensuring your data is trustworthy by improving data reliability is very important.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-data-reliability">What is Data Reliability?</h2>

<p>Data reliability means that data is complete, accurate, and valid. It’s the foundation for building trust in your data across the organization. One of the main objectives of ensuring data reliability is building data trust, which is also used to maintain data security, data quality, and regulatory compliance.</p>

<p>Reliable data helps decision-makers take the guesswork out of the daily and strategic decision-making process to keep their organizations running. But if your data is unreliable, those same decisions become less accurate and can ultimately affect your organization.</p>

<h2 id="why-data-reliability">Why Data Reliability</h2>

<p>When unreliable data is used in making a key strategic decision, it can result in a mistake that damages an organization’s reputation, and bottom line, or even causes its future. Data reliability issues might not seem like a big deal at first glance, but they can snowball over time if left unchecked.</p>

<p>For example, you use customer data to develop targeted online ads or recommend products to your consumers. If the data you use isn’t accurate, then there’s a good chance that the advertising budget will be wasted on either poor results or zero return on investment.</p>

<p>The unsettling feeling when you are not sure if you can trust your data to make a decision can be highly stressful, ut there are actions you can take to improve your data reliability.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-improve-data-reliability">How to Improve Data Reliability</h2>

<p>Like many other managerial tasks, the process to improve your data reliability follows a series of logical steps. There are eight action items that your organization can take to improve your data reliability:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Assess Data Status</li>
  <li>Build Data Infrastructure</li>
  <li>Clean Existing Data</li>
  <li>Optimize Data Collection Processes</li>
  <li>Break Down All Data Silos</li>
  <li>Integrate Data Stack to Connect Data</li>
  <li>Organize Your Data</li>
  <li>Use Reports and Dashboards</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="assess-data-status">Assess Data Status</h3>

<p>Assessing your current data status is the first thing to do to improve data reliability. It helps you to get a general view of how your organization treats data. You should also employ data profiling. Data profiling is the process of examining and analyzing data. This helps you understand if your data is healthy. Assess your current situation to understand:</p>

<p>What are your data sources;
How and where you have stored the data;
How and where you have used the data;
The criteria used to determine data reliability.</p>

<h3 id="build-data-infrastructure">Build Data Infrastructure</h3>

<p>Once you’ve assessed your current situation, you can start updating your data infrastructure. No matter what the original data sources are, you need a secure and easy-to-use data repository. You need to define how your data will be stored, formatted, and organized. There are several steps you can take to create a data infrastructure:</p>

<p>Refine your strategy.
Build a data model.
Choose your data repository type – data lake, data warehouse, or hybrid.
Build an extract, transform, and load (ETL) process.
Implement ongoing data governance.</p>

<h3 id="clean-existing-data">Clean Existing Data</h3>

<p>If you have data sets in place already, you should examine the existing data and remove data that is:</p>

<ul>
  <li>inaccurate;</li>
  <li>incomplete;</li>
  <li>duplicative;</li>
  <li>outdated;</li>
  <li>incorrectly formatted.</li>
</ul>

<p>You should employ data profiling to analyze your data continually, so you can clean, and update data errors as soon as they are spotted.</p>

<h3 id="optimize-data-collection-processes">Optimize Data Collection Processes</h3>

<p>Start by analyzing internal processes for data input. Automate data entry wherever possible to minimize human errors. Make sure that all data entry follows your standardized formats and is accurate, complete, and valid.</p>

<p>Next, look at other data sources you obtain new data from. Make sure that their data formats follow your standardized format and remove inaccurate and unreliable data.</p>

<h3 id="break-down-all-data-silos">Break Down All Data Silos</h3>

<p>Organizations collect data from different departments or locations. This is necessary due to operational requirements or structure setup. But this might create independent data silos that would affect data reliability.</p>

<p>Not only do silos make it difficult to find and share data across your organization, but they also often adhere to different standards of organization and quality.</p>

<p>To ensure the most reliable data is available to those who need it internally, you need to break down your organization’s data silos. You should employ a central data repository for all departments and locations to minimize potential damage to data quality.</p>

<h3 id="integrate-data-stack-to-connect-data">Integrate Data Stack to Connect Data</h3>

<p>Quite often, different departments or locations use various tools and platforms. If you can get everyone to use the same tool and platform, great. If not, you should connect data from these tools and platforms across your entire organization to have a unified view of all your data. Therefore, when a piece of data is updated in one location, it is automatically updated wherever else it is used.</p>

<h3 id="organize-your-data">Organize Your Data</h3>
<p>Every organization has its unique way of organizing data to meet its unique needs. Organizing data makes it easier to locate specific data and speeds up your data retrieval process.</p>

<p>Typically, you will find labels, tags, groups, and other information stored in metadata. Depending on the type and use of your data, you may find data segmented by customer age, gender, geographic location, demographics, etc. No matter how you organize your data, make sure you understand the overall organization’s expectations and what it would like to achieve using the data.</p>

<h3 id="use-reports-and-dashboards">Use Reports and Dashboards</h3>

<p>Finally, make sure you are able to get insight from your data with reports and dashboards. For example, a data profile report can continue to alert you of data errors when it occurs. Other reports that track key metrics in a visual way with detailed analyses put peace of mind in you when it comes to making data-driven decisions.</p>

<h2 id="automate-your-data-reliability-with-piperider">Automate Your Data Reliability With PipeRider</h2>

<p>It may feel overwhelming when you manage a large amount of data, but once you lay the groundwork and build the foundation, there are many tools you can use to make the journey easier. If you’re interested in learning more about your data, with the aim of improving your data reliability, PipeRider can help you.</p>

<p>PipeRider is an open-source, free, and easy-to-use data reliability tool with data profiling and data quality checks through assertions. It executes no-code data profiling and test assertions against your dataset with simple commands. It recommends assertions to save you time and renders your test results into a visual report in minutes. Using the data profiling report you can verify that the data meets your requirements, enabling you to trust your data and make better decisions. PipeRider embraces the modern data stack and connects anywhere on your data pipeline that uses a supported data source.</p>]]></content><author><name>PipeRider</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Modern organizations have gained unprecedented access to quantitative and qualitative data. With all this information available, it’s become best practice for every team to make data-driven decisions. But there’s a problem.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Guide to Data Observability</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/guide-to-data-observability.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Guide to Data Observability" /><published>2022-09-23T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-09-23T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/guide-to-data-observability</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/guide-to-data-observability.html"><![CDATA[<p>The number of data sources that data teams have to deal with is ever increasing. According to a <a href="https://www.matillion.com/resources/blog/matillion-and-idg-survey-data-growth-is-real-and-3-other-key-findings">recent survey</a> by Matillion and IDG, the number of data sources per organization is around 400, with over 20 percent of organizations having 1000 or more. The sheer amount of data makes managing and tracking it increasingly difficult, never mind understanding the bigger picture. That’s where data observability comes in.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-data-observability">What is Data Observability?</h2>

<p>Data observability is the capability to comprehend, assess, and manage the state of data consumed by various technologies throughout the entire data lifecycle.</p>

<p>With data observability, your team can have a better understanding of your data. So they can gather consistent, standardized data from APIs, support data lake observability, facilitate routine queries to data warehouses, and share high-quality data across the entire organization.</p>

<h2 id="why-data-observability">Why Data Observability?</h2>

<p>One of the benefits of data observability is that teams can monitor data pipelines and quickly identify data issues with end-to-end data visibility.</p>

<p>Before data observability, teams might struggle with various data issues such as outdated data, broken data pipelines, or missing data. These issues might be caused by uncertainty in data standards or different data models from different data providers.</p>

<p>With data observability, your team can</p>

<ul>
  <li>standardize data for monitoring;</li>
  <li>debug and triage proactively;</li>
  <li>understand how data interacts with different tools;</li>
  <li>identify issues early;</li>
  <li>minimize the negative impact of data issues.</li>
</ul>

<p>Data observability also makes it possible for your team to automate parts of your monitoring process to constantly improve data quality with less time spent.</p>

<h2 id="what-does-data-observability-track">What Does Data Observability Track?</h2>

<p>Data profiling is an essential part of data observability. Through the following data profiling techniques, you can further understand your data and apply checks that will alert you to issues with your data.</p>

<p>Row-level validation and column-level profiling provide information about the system-wide performance of your data.
Anomaly detection helps spot problems before they damage data quality.
A statistics summary provides an in-depth understanding of the elements of your data observability framework.
Execution metadata and delays analysis throughout data pipelines to prevent data downtime.</p>

<p>These observability techniques should give you a comprehensive insight into the overall data health, potential data issues, and the quality of your data.</p>

<p>Incorporate Data Observability into Work to Improve Data Quality (h2)
According to research, one-third of data analysts spend more than 40 percent of their time on standardizing data to make it ready for analysis, and 57 percent of organizations still regard the “work of transforming their data to be very difficult.” It is obvious that ensuring consistent and accurate data can be a difficult and expensive task for organizations.</p>

<p>Therefore, having proper and solid data observability set up not only saves time but also a lot of resources, including money - But how do you incorporate data observability into your data quality workflow? You should start by developing a framework, then a strategy, and based on these two, choose the right tool for data observability.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-develop-a-data-observability-framework">How to Develop a Data Observability Framework</h2>

<p>Start your data observability journey by creating an efficient data-driven framework focusing on data quality, consistency, and reliability.</p>

<p>A data observability framework should answer the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>How fresh and up-to-date is our data?</li>
  <li>What expected data value should we verify to ensure credible data?</li>
  <li>What data do we need to track and test to see when the data is broken?</li>
  <li>What is the responsibility of each team to various data sets?</li>
  <li>What other workflow, such as gathering metadata, or mapping upstream data sources and downstream users, do we need?</li>
</ul>

<p>The framework should give your team an overall view of standardized data across the organization, letting them quickly identify and fix problems.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-develop-a-data-observability-strategy">How to Develop a Data Observability Strategy</h2>

<p>Once you have a framework in place, many teams may jump right into integrating data observability into the entire data stack. But putting data observability into practice goes beyond the tools you employ.</p>

<p>You should start with preparing your team to adopt a culture of data-driven collaboration. Think about how to integrate data across different teams and sources, and also consider if implementing a new observability tool will affect existing workflow and resources.</p>

<p>Then incorporate the framework into your strategy to determine a standardized library/guidelines with the characteristics of quality data. Your team can use the guidelines to connect data from all sources.</p>

<p>Finally, incorporate your data sources into the observability tool. To obtain the metrics, logs, and traces required to provide end-to-end visibility, you might need to create new observability pipelines. Correlate the metrics you are tracking in your tool with targeted organization goals after adding the governance and data management rules. By using your observability tool to identify and address problems, you can also find new ways to automate some of your data management processes.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-choose-the-right-data-observability-tool">How to Choose the Right Data Observability Tool</h2>

<p>While there’s no one tool to fit every organization’s needs, a good observability tool should be able to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>gather, examine, sample, and process telemetry data from various data sources;</li>
  <li>detect and alert problems in datasets;</li>
  <li>provide end-to-end visibility;</li>
  <li>display data visualizations.</li>
</ul>

<p>In order to choose a suitable data observability tool, you’ll need to examine your current data stack and get a full picture of how data is gathered and distributed. Then you can look into a tool that is ready to integrate all of your data sources. Your chosen tool should be able to monitor your data in real-time throughout its lifecycle and monitor existing data without extraction. In addition, it should also be able to automate your data observability with minimum effort.</p>

<p>Ultimately, your organization’s specific data stack and data engineering requirements will determine the right tool for you. For the best implementation experience, give top priority to finding a tool that requires less work to standardize your data, map your data, or monitor your data.</p>

<h2 id="integrate-data-observability-with-piperider">Integrate Data Observability with PipeRider</h2>

<p>PipeRider is an open-source, free, and easy-to-use data observability tool with data profiling and data quality checks through assertions. It executes no-code data profiling and test assertions against your dataset with simple commands. It recommends assertions to save you time and renders your test results into a visual report in minutes. Using the data profiling report you can verify that the data meets your requirements enabling you to trust your data and make better decisions. PipeRider embraces the modern data stack and connects anywhere on your data pipeline that uses a supported data source.</p>]]></content><author><name>PipeRider</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The number of data sources that data teams have to deal with is ever increasing. According to a recent survey by Matillion and IDG, the number of data sources per organization is around 400, with over 20 percent of organizations having 1000 or more. The sheer amount of data makes managing and tracking it increasingly difficult, never mind understanding the bigger picture. That’s where data observability comes in.]]></summary></entry></feed>